{"tossups": [{"question": "This artist may depict Harman van Swole in a<em> Portrait of a Slav Prince</em> later bought by Catherine the Great. This artist was hired by the Guild of Surgeons in his home nation to paint the dissection of the deceased criminal Aris Kindt. Another work by this man depicts a shooting company led by Franz Banning Cocq [[\"COKE\"]] in<em> The Night Watch</em>. For ten points, name this prolific Dutch artist whose other work includes many self-portraits and<em> The</em> <em>Anatomy Lesson of Dr. Nicolaes Tulp</em>.", "answer": "<b><u>Rembrandt</u></b> <b><u>van Rijn</u></b> (or <b><u>Rembrandt</u></b> Harmenszoon <b><u>van Rijn</u></b>; accept either underlined portion)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {"question": "Medal of Honor-winner Bud Day saved this man's life after he dropped a third of his body weight while in the Vietnamese POW camp called \"The Plantation.\" With Russ Feingold, this senator names a campaign reform bill which limits the amount of \"soft money\" available to candidates. This politician succeeded Barry Goldwater as senator from Arizona in 1987. The 2008 Republican candidate for U.S. president was, for ten points, what politician who died in 2018?", "answer": "John <b><u>McCain</u></b> (or John Sidney <b><u>McCain</u></b> III)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Callimachus [[kah-lee-MAH-kuss]] died at this battle while chasing the losing side to their ships. One side in this battle failed to get reinforcements due to the<em> Carneia</em> [[kar-NAY-uh]] festival. The winning strategy in this battle was created by Miltiades [[mil-TYE-ah-deez]], who defeated the forces of Darius I. A messenger supposedly ran over twenty miles to report this battle's outcome. For ten points, name this battle of the Greco-Persian Wars that inspired a lengthy footrace.", "answer": "Battle of <b><u>Marathon</u></b> (or Mach\u0113 tou <b><u>Marath</u><u>\u014d</u><u>n</u></b>os)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "Comparing it to the French conquest of Algeria, this act was promoted by Charles Sumner in a senate bill. In a political cartoon criticizing this event, a man meant to represent Andrew Johnson lugs around an iceberg in a wheelbarrow. In an effort to avoid British conquest, Tsar Alexander II sent the diplomat Eduard de Stoeckl [[SHTEH-kul]] to execute this sale. For ten points, name this acquisition of a former Russian colony known to detractors as \"Seward's Folly.\"", "answer": "U.S. <b><u>Purchase</u></b> of <b><u>Alaska</u></b> (accept answers which reference <b><u>Buy</u></b>ing <b><u>Alaska</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Iceland was once controlled by, for ten points, what Scandinavian nation governed from Copenhagen?", "answer": "Kingdom of <b><u>Denmark</u></b> (or Kongeriget <b><u>Danmark</u></b>; accept the <b><u>Danish</u></b> Realm; or <b><u>Danmark</u></b>s Rige)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "An injury kept this academic from representing the UK at the 1948 Olympics as a marathon runner. A 2017 \"Law\" named for this scientist provided amnesty to UK men charged under anti-homosexuality legislation. The Battle of the Atlantic began tipping in the favor of the Allies in large part due to this man cracking the German naval Enigma code. A machine which can replicate any computer algorithm is named for, for ten points, which British computer scientist?", "answer": "Alan <b><u>Turing</u></b> (or Alan Mathison <b><u>Turing</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Future Israeli prime minister Menachem Begin [[meh-NAH-kem BEH-gin]] sent a parcel bomb meant to kill this nation's head of state, instead killing police officer Karl Reichert [[\"RYE\"-kert]]. This state's \"Economic Miracle\" was orchestrated by Ludwig Erhard [[EHR-hard]] and Chancellor Konrad Adenauer [[AH-den-ow-uh]]. For ten points, name this country, sometimes known as the \"Bonn Republic,\" which reunified with an eastern communist neighbor in 1990.", "answer": "<b><u>West Germany</u></b> (or <b><u>West Deutschland</u></b>; accept <b><u>Federal Republic of Germany</u></b>; or <b><u>Bundesrepublik Deutschland</u></b>; accept <b><u>FRG</u></b>; or <b><u>BRD</u></b>; do not accept or prompt on  \"Deutschland\" or \"Germany\")", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This politician hired education reformer John Dewey, who suggested switching his country's alphabet to a Latin script. In 1924, this politician formally abolished the last recognized caliph, Abdulmejid II. Following this man's failure to get the League of Nations to annul the Treaty of S\u00e8vres [[SEH-vruh]], this head of the Ankara government launched an invasion of the Greek zone of occupation. The father of modern Turkey was, for ten points, which 20th century politician?", "answer": "Mustafa Kemal <b><u>Atat\u00fcrk</u></b> (or Mustafa Kemal <b><u>Pasha</u></b>; accept Ali Riza oglu <b><u>Mustafa</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "The geology concept known as stratigraphy was applied to this science by Danish antiquarian Christian J\u00fcrgensen Thomsen. William Cunnington, a founding father of this science, conducted a series of expeditions to Wiltshire, where he recorded findings in barrows. Notable developments in this science include the discoveries of Hissarlik in Turkey and Mycenae [[my-SEE-nee]] in Greece by Heinrich Schliemann [[SHLEE-mahn]]. For ten points, name this science which conducts excavations of ancient sites.", "answer": "<b><u>Archaeology</u></b> (accept <b><u>Archaeologist</u></b>s; accept <b><u>Excavation</u></b> before mentioned; prompt on \"Antiquarianism\" before \"antiquarian\")", "metadata": "Social Science - Social Science - Anthropology"}, {"question": "The island of Gotland in this sea was the home of the Victual [[VIC-too-all]] Brothers, enemies of the Hanseatic [[HAN-see-at-ik]] League, a trading network of ports around this sea. The ports of Gda\u0144sk [[guh-DANSK]] and Stockholm lie on this body of water, and the city of Saint Petersburg was created by Peter the Great to ensure Russian access to this sea. For ten points, name this large sea in northern Europe, named for an ancient tribe from what is now Lithuania and Latvia.", "answer": "<b><u>Baltic</u></b> Sea(accept <b><u>Ostsee</u></b> and variations; accept <b><u>L\u00e4\u00e4nemeri</u></b>; accept <b><u>It\u00e4meri</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "This general received his nickname after serving with the 10th Cavalry of the Buffalo Soldiers. In one conflict, this man's forces first engaged with the enemy at Cantigny [[kahn-teen-YEE]] and Belleau [[\"BELLOW\"]] Woods. This man commanded the \"dough boys\" during the Meuse-Argonne [[myuhs-ahr-GOHN]] Offensive, as well as assisting British and French forces in the Hundred Days Offensive. For ten points, name this General of the Armies and leader of the American Expeditionary Forces during World War One.", "answer": "John \"Black Jack\" <b><u>Pershing</u></b> (or John Joseph \"Black Jack\" <b><u>Pershing</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "This man's work as a secretary has led to debate over how much of his personal philosophy went into the<em> Fundamental Constitutions of Carolina</em>, which espoused aristocracy and slavery. One work by this thinker outlines the \"State of Nature\" and claims that society was built to protect property, which he defined as \"life, liberty, and estate,\" inspiring Thomas Jefferson. For ten points, name this English empiricist and \"Father of Liberalism\" who wrote <em>Two Treatises of Government</em>.", "answer": "John <b><u>Locke</u></b>", "metadata": "Philosophy - Philosophy"}, {}, {"question": "The Battle of New Orleans occurred in, for ten points, which southern U.S. state?", "answer": "<b><u>Louisiana</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "Following this event, Enver Hoxha [[HODJ-uh]] pulled Albania out of the Warsaw Pact. In protest of the end of this event, student Jan Palach [[YAHN pah-LAHK]] set himself on fire in Wenceslas [[WEN-seh-slahss]] Square. Military intervention during this event was justified by the Brezhnev Doctrine. The reforms of Alexander Dub\u010dek [[DOOB-chek]] led to, for ten points, what 1968 period of liberalization that was crushed by Soviet intervention in the namesake Czech city?", "answer": "<b><u>Prague Spring</u></b> (accept <b><u>Pra</u><u>\u017e</u><u>sk\u00e9 Jaro</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "During this period, the art of lone storytelling called<em> rakugo</em> grew in popularity as the<em> Ch\u014dnin</em> middle class emerged. This period began following a victory by the \"Eastern Army\" over Toyotomi [[toh-yoh-TOH-mee]] loyalists at the Battle of Sekigahara [[seh-kee-gah-HAH-rah]]. This period's ruling dynasty was weakened when Commodore Matthew Perry forced an end to<em> Sakoku</em> isolation. A clan of Shoguns established by Ieyasu [[ee-eh-YAH-soo]] ruled from modern-day Tokyo in what historical Japanese period?", "answer": "<b><u>Tokugawa</u></b> Shogunate (or <b><u>Tokugawa</u></b> Bakufu; accept <b><u>Tokugawa</u></b> Period or Jidai; accept <b><u>Edo</u></b> Period or Jidai)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "Don Pellegrini is executed in this city by a Nazi occupation force led by Major Bergmann in a Rossellini film set in this city, which began his \"Neo-realist Trilogy.\" A young Audrey Hepburn appears as Princess Ann in a 1951 film titled for a \"Holiday\" in this city, visiting sites like the Spanish steps and the Trevi fountain.<em> Ben-Hur's</em> chariot-racing scene occurs in the Colosseum of, for ten points, which Italian capital city?", "answer": "<b><u>Rome</u></b> (accept <em><b><u>Rome</u></b>, Open City</em>; accept <em><b><u>Roman</u></b> Holiday</em>)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Other Fine Arts - Film"}, {}, {"question": "<b><u>The Rogers Commission was created to investigate this incident, which saw the</u> <u>deaths of Ronald McNair and Francis R. Scobee, among others. Barbara Morgan was</u> <u>(+)</u> the backup to an intended historical first before this incident, which resulted in a thirty-two month hiatus for one program. Christa McAuliffe, the face of the Teacher in Space Program, died during this Reagan-era (*)</b> incident. For ten points, name this 1986 disaster in which a Space Shuttle disintegrated 73 seconds after launch.", "answer": "Space Shuttle <em><b><u>Challenger</u></b></em> Disaster (accept descriptive answers involving the <b><u>Challenger</u></b> disaster)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>This president\u2019s Secretary of the Treasury nominee, Caleb Cushing, was</u> <u>rejected by Congress three times in one day. This man's Secretary of State, Abel P.</u> <u>Upshur, and Navy Secretary, Thomas Walker Gilmer, died in an explosion aboard the</u> <u>USS (+)</u></b> <em><b>Princeton</b></em><b>. This president opposed Henry Clay\u2019s American System despite running on the Whig ticket. (*)</b> For ten points, name this president dubbed \u201cHis Accidency,\u201d who succeeded William Henry Harrison.", "answer": "John <b><u>Tyler</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>The</u></b><em><b><u> Ecclesiastical Ordinances</u></b></em><b><u> of King Cnut [[CAH-noot]] defined certain laws so</u> <u>that these \"madly audacious\" creatures \"do not too widely devastate, nor bite too</u> <u>many of the spiritual flock.\" The geographer Pausanias [[pow-SAY-nee-us]] described</u> <u>how King (+)</u> Lycaon [[\"lie\"-KAY-on]] became one of these creatures after sacrificing a child to Zeus. Modern fiction describes these monsters as being vulnerable to objects cast from (*)</b> silver. For ten points, name these historically-feared creatures that transform into dangerous canines during the full moon.", "answer": "<b><u>Werewolf</u></b> (or <b><u>Lycanthrope</u></b>; prompt on \"wolf\"; prompt on \"shapeshifter\"; accept plurals)", "metadata": "Mythology - Mythology"}, {"question": "<b><u>Early attempts to sail this route included attempts to find the mythical Strait of</u> <u>Ani\u00e1n [[ah-nee-AHN]], which was allegedly traversed by Juan de Fuca. This route was</u> <u>the intended goal of John (+)</u> Cabot's east-west voyage, as well as Jacques Cartier's expedition into the Gulf of Saint Lawrence. Robert McClure was the first to sail this ice-bound (*)</b> route from 1850 to 1854. For ten points, name this sea route between that Atlantic and Pacific Oceans that crosses through the Arctic.", "answer": "<b><u>Northwest Passage</u></b> (accept word forms; accept descriptive answers before \"Atlantic\")", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {}, {"question": "<b><u>A fake story suggested Ronald Reagan was intended to play the lead in this</u> <u>historical fiction movie. This film was released early to capitalize on free press from</u> <u>Operation (+)</u> Torch, the allied invasion of North Africa. This movie ends with Louis suggesting he join the Free French with Rick Blaine, who states, \"I think this is the beginning of a (*)</b> beautiful friendship.\" For ten points, what Humphrey Bogart and Ingrid Bergman Best Picture winner is named for a Moroccan city?", "answer": "<em><b><u>Casablanca</u></b></em>", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "<b><u>This man lost a Connecticut congressional run to his cousin and future</u> <u>chairman of the DNC, William Henry. This man purported that a former enslaved</u> <u>person named Joice Heth was, in fact, the 161 year old nurse (+)</u> of George Washington. This man, who unveiled the first aquarium in the U.S., hired performers (*)</b> such as the dwarf Tom Thumb and the operatic singer Jenny Lind. James Anthony Bailey paired with, for ten points, which showman to create a namesake 20th century circus?", "answer": "P.T. <b><u>Barnum</u></b> (or Phineas Taylor <b><u>Barnum</u></b>; accept Ringling Brothers & <b><u>Barnum</u> </b>and Bailey Circus)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>This man's death by road accident in the Dorset countryside in 1935 led</u> <u>neurosurgeon Hugh Cairns to develop the motorcycle helmet. This intelligence officer</u></b> <b>proved</b> <b>vital</b> <b>in</b> <b>the</b> <b>capture</b> <b>of</b> <b>Aqaba</b> <b>[[AH-kah-bah]]</b> <b>(+)</b> <b>by</b> <b>allied</b> <b>Hejazi</b> <b>[[heh-JAH-zee]] forces. This man's autobiography,</b><em><b> Seven Pillars of Wisdom</b></em><b>, concerns his involvement in the Arab Revolt. (*)</b> For ten points, name this British officer whose efforts in World War One inspired a film starring Peter O'Toole.", "answer": "<b><u>Lawrence</u></b> of Arabia (or T(homas) E(dward) <b><u>Lawrence</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b><u>The prevalence of these people led the citizens of Sarawak to crown the \"White</u> <u>Rajah\" James Brooke after he agreed to drive them out of the nation. Until their</u> <u>decline after the Treaty of Gyehae [[\"guy\"-HAY]], a group of these people called the</u> </b><em><b><u>Wokou</u></b></em><b><u> (+)</u> plagued the Ming Dynasty. Julius Caesar was captured and ransomed by Cilician [[sih-LIH-shun]] men in this profession, whom he later crucified for their crimes. (*)</b> For ten points, name this profession characterized by robbery and extortion via ship.", "answer": "<b><u>Pirate</u></b>s (accept <b><u>Privateer</u></b>s; or <b><u>Buccaneer</u></b>s)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "<b><u>Like the Ancient Egyptians, this civilization depicted women as white-skinned</u> <u>and men as red. This civilization's deities were primarily female, such as a snake</u> <u>goddess, and its people honored them through the display of double-headed axes and</u> <u>the sport of (+)</u> bull leaping. Arthur Evans was the first to distinguish this civilization from the later Myceneans [[MY-seh-NEE-ens]], although he was unable to (*)</b> decipher its \"linear\" script. For ten points, name this proto-Greek civilization of Crete.", "answer": "<b><u>Minoan</u></b>s (prompt on \"Proto-Greek\" before mentioned)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {}], "bonuses": []}